It began with one question:
لقد بدأ الموضوع بسؤال واحد:
If Africa was a bar, what would your country be drinking or doing?
إذا كانت أفريقيا حانة فماذا سيشرب بلدك أو يفعل ؟
I kicked it off with a guess about South Africa,
و طردت الفكرة بالتفكير في جنوب أفريقيا
which wasn't exactly according to the rules
التي لم تكن ضمن القواعد تماماً
because South Africa's not my country.
لأن جنوب أفريقيا ليست بلدي.
But alluding to the country's continual attempts
ولكن نظرا لمحاولات هذا البلد المستمرة
to build a postracial society
في بناء مجتمع ما بعد العنصرية
after being ravaged for decades by apartheid,
بعد الدمار نتيجة عقود من الفصل العنصري
I tweeted, #ifafricawasabar South Africa would be drinking all kinds of alcohol
فقد نشرت تغريدة في موقعي بأن جنوب أفريقيا ستشرب كل أنواع الكحول
and begging them to get along in its stomach.
و تتوسل بها أن تتمازج في بطنها.
And then I waited.
ثم أنتظرت.
And then I had that funny feeling where I wondered if I crossed the line.
ثم جاءني ذلك الأحساس بأني قد أكون تجاوزت الحدود.
So, I sent out a few other tweets about my own country
ثم نشرت تغريدات أخرى حول بلدي الشخصي
and a few other African countries I'm familiar with.
أو عن بعض البلدان الأفريقية الأخرى التي أعرفها جيدا.
And then I waited again,
ثم أنتظرت مرة أخرى،
but this time
ولكن هذه المرة
I read through almost every tweet I had ever tweeted
وأنا أقرأ تقريباً كل تغريدة كتبتها
to convince myself,
لأقنع نفسي،
no, to remind myself that I'm really funny
كلا، لتذكير نفسي بأنني فعلاً مضحكة
and that if nobody gets it, that's fine.
وإن لم يفهمها أحد, فهذا جيد.
But luckily,
ولكن لحسن الحظ،
I didn't have to do that for very long.
لم يكن عليّ فعل ذلك لفترة طويلة.
Very soon, people were participating.
و بسرعة، بدأت الناس بالمشاركة.
In fact, by the end of that week in July,
في الواقع، و قبل نهاية ذلك الأسبوع في تموز (يوليو)
the hashtag #ifafricawasabar
كان موقعي ifafricawasabar#
would have garnered around 60,000 tweets,
قد حصد حوالي 60000 تغريدة،
lit up the continent
أنارت القارة
and made its way to publications all over the world.
و دفعتها لأحذ طريقها للنشر حول العالم.
People were using the hashtag to do many different things.
كان الناس يستخدمون موقع التغريدة لعمل أشياء عديدة مختلفة.
To poke fun at their stereotypes:
للكز الضاحك في تعابيرهم الضاحكة:
[#IfAfricaWasABar Nigeria would be outside explaining
كتبت إحداهن, لو كان نيجيريا
that he will pay the entrance fee,
قسيدفع رسم الدخول,
all he needs is the bouncer's account details.]
و يحتاج فقط لرقم حساب حماية النادي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
To criticize government spending:
إنتقاداً لطريقة الانفاق الحكومي ،
[#ifafricawasabar South Africa would be ordering bottles it can't pronounce
كما كتبت إن جنوب أفريقيا ستطلب قناني لا يمكنها لفظ إسمها
running a tab it won't be able to pay]
وفتح حنفية لن تكون قادرة على دفعها.
To make light of geopolitical tensions:
لوضع الضوء على التوترات الجيوسياسية:
[#IfAfricaWasABar South Sudan would be the new guy
أضافت أما جنوب السودان فسيكون الشاب الجديد
with serious anger management issues.]
القادم مع مواضيع ادارة الغضب الجدية.
To remind us that even in Africa
لتذكيرنا بأنه حتى في أفريقيا
there are some countries we don't know exist:
هناك بعض البلدان التي لا نعرف حتى بوجودها:
[#IfAfricaWasABar Lesotho would be that person
قالت: ليسوتو ستكون ذلك الشخص
who nobody really knows but is always in the pictures.]
الذي لا يعرفه أحد لكنه دائما في الصورة.
And also to make fun of the countries that don't think that they're in Africa:
وكذلك للضحك على بلدان لا نعتقد بأنها في افريقيا:
[#IfAfricaWasABar Egypt, Libya, Tunisia, Algeria and Morocco
مثل مصر و ليبيا و تونس و الجزائر و المغرب
be like "What the hell are we doing here?!!"]
مثل "اللعنة, ماذا يفعل هؤلاء هنا؟!!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And to note the countries that had made a big turnaround:
ونلاحظ أن بعض الدول قامت بالتحول:
[#ifAfricawasabar Rwanda would be that girl
فقالت ستكون رواندا فتاة
that comes with no money and no transport but leaves drunk, happy and rich]
تأتي بلا نقود ولاسيارة لكنها تغادر سكرانة و سعيدة و غنية
But most importantly,
و لكن الأهم ،
people were using the hashtag to connect.
أن الناس كانوا يستخدمون الهاشتاغ للأتصال.
People were connecting over their Africanness.
كان الناس يتصلون بحسهم الأفريقي.
So for one week in July,
لذلك ولفترة أسبوع في يوليو
Twitter became a real African bar.
أصبح موقع تويتر حانة أفريقية.
And I was really thrilled,
وقد أثارني ذلك فعلاً،
mainly because I realized that Pan-Africanism could work,
لأنني أساساً اكتشفت بأن الوحدة الأفريقية يمكن أن تكون ذات فائدة
that we had before us, between us, at our fingertips
بأن أمامنا وبيننا وقرب أطراف أصابعنا
a platform that just needed a small spark
قاعدة كل ما تحتاجه هو شرارة صغيرة
to light in us a hunger for each other.
لتشعل فينا جوعنا وحاجتنا لبعضنا البعض.
My name is Siyanda Mohutsiwa,
أسمي سياندا موهيتسيوا
I'm 22 years old
و عمري 22 سنة
and I am Pan-Africanist by birth.
وأنا أفريقية منذ ولادتي.
Now, I say I'm Pan-Africanist by birth
حسناً , أقول أنا أفريقية منذ ولادتي
because my parents are from two different African countries.
لأن أبويّ من بلدين أفريقيين مختلفين.
My father's from a country called Botswana in southern Africa.
والدي من بلد أسمه بوتسوانا في جنوب أفريقيا
It's only slightly bigger than Germany.
إنه أكبر قليلا من ألمانيا.
This year we celebrate our 50th year of stable democracy.
و نحتفل هذا العام بذكرى 50 سنة من الديمقراطية المستقرة
And it has some very progressive social policies.
و لديه بعض السياسات الأجتماعية التقدمية جداً.
My mother's country is the Kingdom of Swaziland.
و بلد والدتي هو مملكة سوازيلاند.
It's a very, very small country, also in southern Africa.
و هي بلد صغير جداً جداً في جنوب أفريقيا أيضاً
It is Africa's last complete monarchy.
إنها آخر ممالك أفريفيا الكاملة.
So it's been ruled by a king and a royal family
أي إنها تحكم من قبل ملك و عائلة ملكية
in line with their tradition,
وفق تقاليدهم ،
for a very long time.
منذ مدة طويلة جداً.
On paper, these countries seem very different.
و على الورق ، يبدو هذين البلدين مخنلفين جداً ،
And when I was a kid, I could see the difference.
و عندما كنت طفلة كنت أرى الفرق.
It rained a lot in one country, it didn't rain quite as much in the other.
كانت تمطر كثيراً في أحد البلدين, لكنها لم تمطر كثيراً في البلد الآخر.
But outside of that, I didn't really realize
ولكن خلاف ذلك، لم أميز فعلاً
why it mattered that my parents were from two different places.
لماذا يهم عتدما يكون والديّ من مكانين مختلفين.
But it would go on to have a very peculiar effect on me.
و لكن أستمر هذا ليكون له تأثيرا ًغريباً عليّ
You see, I was born in one country
حسنا، لقد ولدت في واحد من البلدين
and raised in the other.
و تربيت في البلد الآخر.
When we moved to Botswana,
عندما أنتقللنا إلى بوتسوانا ،
I was a toddler who spoke fluent SiSwati
كنت لا أزال طفلة صغيرة وأتكلم سيسواتي بطلاقة
and nothing else.
وليس غير ذلك.
So I was being introduced to my new home,
و هكذا جرى تقديمي الى منزلي الجديد ،
my new cultural identity,
هويتي الثقافية الجديدة،
as a complete outsider,
كغريبة تماماً ،
incapable of comprehending anything that was being said to me
غير قابلة على إستيعاب أي شئ مما يقال لي
by the family and country whose traditions I was meant to move forward.
من قبل العائلة أو بلدي و تقاليدهم التي تريدني أن أتقدم الى الأمام.
But very soon, I would shed SiSwati.
ولكن سريعاً ما نسيت سيسواتي.
And when I would go back to Swaziland,
وعندما سأعود مستقبلاً إلى سوازيلاند,
I would be constantly confronted by how very non-Swazi I was becoming.
سأجابه بشكل مستمر بكيفية كيف أصبحت غير سوازية.
Add to that my entry into Africa's private school system,
و أضيف إلى ذلك دخولي في نظام المدارس الخاصة فيي أفريقيا
whose entire purpose is to beat the Africanness out of you,
التي كل الهدف منها هو التغلب على أفريقيتنا فينا ،
and I would have a very peculiar adolescence.
وستكون لدي فترة مراهقة غريبة.
But I think that my interest in ideas of identity was born here,
و لكني أظن بأن إهتمامي بأفكار الهوية ولدت هنا ،
in the strange intersection of belonging to two places at once
عند التقاطع الغريب للارتباط بمكانين في وقت واحد.
but not really belonging to either one very well
ولكن عدم الارتباط فعلاً بأي منهما
and belonging to this vast space in between and around simultaneously.
و الأرتباط بهذا الفضاء الشاسع الذي يحيط بنا و بيننا في نفس الوقت.
I became obsessed with the idea of a shared African identity.
و تلبستني فكرة هوية أفريقية مشتركة.
Since then, I have continued to read about politics
و منذ ذلك الوقت, بدأت بقراءة كل شئ عن السياسة
and geography and identity and what all those things mean.
و الجغرافيا و الهوية وما تعنيه كل هذه الأشياء.
I've also held on to a deep curiosity about African philosophies.
كما انتابني فضول عميق حول الفلسفات الأفريقية.
When I began to read,
وعندما بدأت بالقراءة ،
I gravitated towards the works of black intellectuals
شدتني أعمال المثقفين السود
like Steve Biko and Frantz Fanon,
مثل ستيف بيكو و فرانتز فانون,
who tackled complex ideas
اللذين ناقشا أفكاراً معقدة
like decolonization and black consciousness.
مثل تغيير اللون و الضمير الأسود.
And when I thought, at 14, that I had digested these grand ideas,
وعندما أعتقدت في سن 14, بأنني قد هضمت هذه الأفكار العظيمة ،
I moved on to the speeches of iconic African statesmen
فتحولت إلى خطابات رموز رجال دولة أفارقة
like Burkina Faso's Thomas Sankara
مثل توماس سانكارا من بوركينا فاسو
and Congo's Patrice Lumumba.
و بياتريس لومومبا من الكونغو.
I read every piece of African fiction that I could get my hands on.
لقد قرأت كل قصة من القصص الأفريقية وقعت عليها يدي.
So when Twitter came,
لذلك عندما جاءت تويتر,
I hopped on with the enthusiasm of a teenage girl
قفزت فيها بكل شوق لبنت مراهقة
whose friends are super, super bored of hearing about all this random stuff.
التي لها أصدقاء ضجرين جدا جدا من سماع ما تقوله عن الحديث العشوائي.
The year was 2011
كانت السنة 2011
and all over southern Africa and the whole continent,
وعلى إمتداد جنوب أفريقيا و في مجمل القارة
affordable data packages for smartphones and Internet surfing
أصبحت رزم البيانات الرخيصة الثمن للهواتف الذكية و البحث في الأنترنت
became much easier to get.
متوفرة بسهولة .
So my generation, we were sending messages to each other on this platform
و هكذا أصبح جيلي, يرسل الرسائل واحداً للآخر على هذه المساحة
that just needed 140 characters and a little bit of creativity.
كل ما تحتاجه هو 140 حرفاً و قليل من الموهبة الخلاقة.
On long commutes to work,
في الرحلات الطويلة الى العمل ،
in lectures that some of us should have been paying attention to,
و في المحاضرات التي كان علينا الأنتباه لها ،
on our lunch breaks,
في فرصة الغداء،
we would communicate as much as we could
يمكننا التواصل قدر ما نريد
about the everyday realities of being young and African.
حول كل وقائعنا اليومية كشباب و أفارقة.
But of course, this luxury was not available to everybody.
ولكن بالطبع لم يكن ذلك متوفراً للجميع.
So this meant that if you were a teenage girl in Botswana
و يعني هذا انك لو كنت فتاة مراهقة من بوتسوانا
and you wanted to have fun on the Internet,
وأردت أن تتمتعي بوقتك على الأنترنت ،
one, you had to tweet in English.
أولاً، يجب عليك كتابة التغريدات بالأنكليزية
Two, you had to follow more than just the three other people you knew online.
ثانياً، عليك أن تتابعي أكثر من ثلاثة اشخاص تعرفينهم على الأنترنت.
You had to follow South Africans, Zimbabweans, Ghanaians, Nigerians.
عليكي أن تتابعي أفراد من جنوب أفريقيا ومن زمبابوي و غانا و نيجيريا.
And suddenly, your whole world opened up.
و فجأة ينفتح العالم كله أمامك.
And my whole world did open up.
و قد انفتح عالمي كله أمامي
I followed vibrant Africans who were travelling around the continent,
و تابعت الأفارقة النشطاء الذين كانوا يسافرون في أرجاء القارة ،
taking pictures of themselves
و يأخذون الصور لأنفسهم
and posting them under the hashtag #myafrica.
و ينشرونها في موقع أفريقيا لي.
Because at that time,
لأنك في هذا الوقت,
if you were to search Africa on Twitter or on Google
لو أردت البحث عن أفربقبا على تويتر أو غوغل
or any kind of social media,
أو أي نوع من وسائل التواصل الأجتماعي
you would think that the entire continent was just pictures of animals
كنت ستعتقد بأن كل القارة هي عبارة عن صور حيوانات
and white guys drinking cocktails in hotel resorts.
أو رجال بيض يحتسون الشراب في فنادق سياحية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But Africans were using this platform
و لكن الأفارقة كانوا يستخدمون هذه الوسائل
to take some kind of ownership of the tourism sectors.
للحصول على ملكية قطاعات السياحة.
It was Africans taking selfies on the beaches of Nigeria.
كان الأفارقة يصورون أنفسهم على شواطئ نيجيريا.
It was Africans in cocktail bars in Nairobi.
و كانوا أفارقة في نوادي الشراب في نايروبي
And these were the same Africans that I began to meet
وكان هؤلاء هم الأفارقة الذين بدأت اقابلهم
in my own travels around the continent.
في رحلاتي الخاصة في أرجاء القارة.
We would discuss African literature, politics, economic policy.
كنا نناقش الأدب الأفريقي و السياسة والاقتصاد الأفريقي.
But almost invariably, every single time,
و كنا غالبا و في كل مرة ،
we would end up discussing Twitter.
ننتهي بمناقشة التويتر.
And that's when I realized what this was.
وهذا عندما أدركت ما كان ذلك.
We were standing in the middle of something amazing,
كنا نقف في وسط شيء مدهش
because for the first time ever
لأنه للمرة الأولى
young Africans could discuss the future of our continent in real time,
يناقش الأفارقة الشباب مستقبل قارتنا مباشرة
without the restriction of borders, finances and watchful governments.
دون تقييدات الحدود والتمويل و مراقبة الحكومات
Because the little known truth is
لأن الحقيقة البسيطة المعروفة هي
many Africans know a lot less about other African countries
أن الكثير من الافارقة يعرفون أقل عن الدول الأفريقية الأخرى
than some Westerners might know about Africa as a whole.
مما قد يعرفه الغربيون عن أفريقيا ككل.
This is by accident,
وكان هذا صدفة ،
but sometimes, it's by design.
لكنه أحياناً بموجب خطة.
For example, in apartheid South Africa,
مثلاً، في جنوب أفريقيا العنصرية ،
black South Africans were constantly being bombarded
كان يتم إفهام الأفارقة السود باستمرار
with this message that any country ruled by black people
بالرسالة التي تقول إن كل بلد يحكمه السود
was destined for failure.
يكون مصيره الفشل.
And this was done to convince them
وكان هذا يتم لأقناعهم
that they were much better off under crushing white rule
بأن حالهم أحسن بكثير تحت حكم البيض المدمر
than they were living in a black and free nation.
من حاله لو كانوا يعيشون في بلد أسود و حر.
Add to that Africa's colonial, archaic education system,
أضف الى ذلك النظام الأستعماري القديم في أفريقيا
which has been unthinkingly carried over from the 1920s --
والذي كان معمولاً به بلا تفكير منذ 1920 --
and at the age of 15, I could name all the various causes
و في عمر 15 عاماً كنت قادرة أن أكتب جميع الأسباب المختلفة
of the wars that had happened in Europe in the past 200 years,
للحروب التي حدثت في أوروبا خلال المائتي سنة الماضية ،
but I couldn't name the president of my neighboring country.
و لكني لم أكن أعرف إسم رئيس الدولة المجاورة.
And to me, this doesn't make any sense
و لم يكن هذا معقولاً بالنسبة لي
because whether we like it or not,
لأننا لو كنا نريد أو لا نريد ذلك ،
the fates of African people are deeply intertwined.
قإن مصير كل الأفارقة متشابك بشدة.
When disaster hits, when turmoil hits,
فعندما تضرب الكوارث و عندما تضطرب الأمور
we share the consequences.
فإننا نشترك بكل ما يترتب علي ذلك.
When Burundians flee political turmoil,
عندما يهرب البورنديون من الأضطراب السياسي
they go to us,
يأتون إلينا ،
to other African countries.
إلى بلدان أفريقية أخرى.
Africa has six of the world's largest refugee centers.
لدى أفريقيا ستة من أكبر مراكز اللاجئين.
What was once a Burundian problem
و ما كان مرة مشكلة بورندية
becomes an African problem.
أصبح مشكلة أفريقية.
So to me, there are no Sudanese problems
لذا و بالنسبة لي لا توجد مشاكل سودانية
or South African problems or Kenyan problems,
أو مشاكل جنوب أفريقية أو مشاكل كينية ،
only African problems
يوجد فقط مشاكل أفريقية
because eventually, we share the turmoil.
لأننا فعلاً نتشارك في الأضطراب.
So if we share the problems,
لذلك و مادمنا نتشارك المشاكل
why aren't we doing a better job of sharing the successes?
لم لا نعمل أحسن بإشتراكنا بالنجاحات؟
How can we do that?
كيف يمكن أن نعمل ذلك؟
Well, in the long term,
حسناً،على المدى البعيد
we can shoot towards increasing inter-African trade,
يمكن أن نستهدف زيادة التجارة البينية الأفريقية
removing borders and putting pressure on leaders
و إزالة الحدود والضغط أكثر على القيادات
to fulfill regional agreements they've already signed.
للألتزام بالأتفاقات الاقليمية التي سبق أن وقعوها.
But I think that the biggest way for Africa to share its successes
و لكني أعتقد بأن أكبر طريقة لأفريقيا لمشاركة نجاحاتها
is to foster something I like to call social Pan-Africanism.
هو تبني شيء أحب أن اسميه الأمة الأفريقية.
Now, political Pan-Africanism already exists,
والآن فإن الأمة الأفريقية السياسية موجودة فعلاً
so I'm not inventing anything totally new here.
لذلك فأنا لا أخترع أي شيء جديد هنا.
But political Pan-Africanism
و لكن الأمة الأفريقية السياسية
is usually the African unity of the political elite.
هي عادة الوحدة الأفريقية للنخبة السياسية.
And who does that benefit?
ومن المستفيد من ذلك؟
Well, African leaders, almost exclusively.
حسناً، إنهم القادة الأفارقة بشكل حصري تقريباً.
No, what I'm talking about
كلا، ما أتحدث عنه هو
is the Pan-Africanism of the ordinary African.
الأمة الأفريقية للأفارقة العاديين.
Young Africans like me,
للأفارقة الشباب مثلي ،
we are bursting with creative energy,
نحن نتفجر طاقة خلاقة
with innovative ideas.
بأفكار مبتكرة .
But with bad governance and shaky institutions,
ولكن بوجود حاكمية سيئة و معاهد مهتزة ،
all of this potential could go to waste.
فإن كل هذه الأمكانيات ستذهب سدى
On a continent where more than a handful of leaders
و في قارة حيث يمسك عدد قليل من القادة
have been in power longer
بالسلطة لفترة أطول
than the majority of the populations has been alive,
من أعمار غالبية السكان,
we are in desperate need of something new,
فنحن في حاجة يائسة لشيء جديد
something that works.
شيء يمكن أن يفيد.
And I think that thing is social Pan-Africanism.
و أعتقد أن هذا الشيء هو الأمة الأفريقية الأجتماعية.
My dream is that young Africans
إن حلمي هو أن يتوقف جميع الشباب الأفارقة
stop allowing borders and circumstance to suffocate our innovation.
عن السماح للحدود و الظروف بخنق ابتكاراتنا.
My dream is that when a young African comes up with something brilliant,
إن حلمي هو إنه عندما يأتي شاب أفريقيي بشيء عبقري
they don't say, "Well, this wouldn't work in my country,"
لا يقولون له, "حسناً إن هذا لن يعمل في بلدي."
and then give up.
و حينئذ يستسلم.
My dream is that young Africans begin to realize
حلمي بأن يبدأ الأفارقة الشباب بفهم
that the entire continent is our canvas, is our home.
أن كل القارة هي نسيجنا و بيتنا.
Using the Internet, we can begin to think collaboratively,
و بإستخدام الأنترنت يمكن أن نبدأ بالتفكير بشكل تعاوني
we can begin to innovate together.
يمكننا أن نبدأ بالأبتكار معاً.
In Africa, we say, "If you want to go fast, you go alone,
نقول في افريقيا"إذا أردت المشي سريعا عليك السير منفرداً
but if you want to go far, you go together."
و لكن إذا أردت المشي إلى أبعد, فعليك السير مع أحد."
And I believe that social Pan-Africanism is how we can go far together.
وأعتقد إن الأمة الأفريقية الأجتماعية هي طريقنا للسير معا.
And this is already happening.
و هذا ما يحدث الآن فعلاً.
Access to these online networks has given young Africans
لقد أعطى الدخول إلى شبكات التواصل الأفارقة الشباب
something we've always had to violently take: a voice.
شيئا طالما أردنا بشدة أن نحصل عليه: أعطانا صوتاً.
We now have a platform.
حيث انه لدينا الآن قاعدة.
Before now, if you wanted to hear from the youth in Africa,
و قبل هذا إذا أردت سماع شاب من أفريقيا
you waited for the 65-year-old minister of youth --
كنت ستتنتظر صوت وزير الشباب الذي عمره 65 عاما --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
to wake up in the morning,
ليستيقظ في الصباح,
take his heartburn medication
و يأخذ أدوية الحموضة و الحرقة
and then tell you the plans he has for your generation
ثم ليخبرك عن الخطط التي لديه لجيلك
in 20 years time.
خلال العشرين سنة القادمة.
Before now, if you wanted to be heard by your possibly tyrannical government,
و قبل الآن إذا كنت تريد إسماع صوتك إلى حكومتك التي قد تكون دكتاتورية
you were pushed to protest, suffer the consequences
كنت تدفع للأحتجاج و تحمل النتائج
and have your fingers crossed
و تدعو مخلصاً
that some Western paper somewhere might make someone care.
بأن احدى الصحف الغربية في مكان ما قد تجعل شخصاً ما يهتم.
But now we have opportunities to back each other up
و لكن لدينا الفرصة بأن يدعم أحدنا الآخر
in ways we never could before.
بطرق لم يمكننا استخدامها من قبل.
We support South African students
نحن نساند الطلاب من جنوب أفريقيا
who are marching against ridiculously high tertiary fees.
الذين يقومون بمسيرات ضد أجور التعليم العالي الغالية.
We support Zimbabwean women who are marching to parliament.
و نساند النساء من زمبابوي في مسيرتهن نحو البرلمان.
We support Angolan journalists who are being illegally detained.
و ندعم الصحفيين من أنغولا المحتجزون دون مبرر قانوني.
For the first time ever,
و لأول مرة في التاريخ
African pain and African aspiration
يكون للألم الأفريقي و التطلعات الأفريقية
has the ability to be witnessed
القدرة بالحصول على شاهد
by those who can empathize with it the most:
من أولئك الذين يمكنهم التعاطف أكثر:
other Africans.
الأفارقة الآخرون.
I believe that with a social Pan-Africanist thinking
أعتقد بأننا مع التفكير بالأمة الأفريقية الأجتماعية
and using the Internet as a tool,
و بإستخدام الأنترنت كأداة
we can begin to rescue each other,
يمكن أن نبدأ بمساعدة أحدنا الآخر ،
and ultimately, to rescue ourselves.
و في النهاية مساعدة أنفسنا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)